Finding Aid for John G. Parkhurst papers, 1802-1914
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John G. Parkhurst papers 1802-1914
Parkhurst, John G. (John Gibson), 1824-1906.
852268 Aa 2; Ac
Lawyer at Coldwater, Michigan, Civil War officer, U.S. Marshal of Eastern District of Michigan and Minister to Belgium. Correspondence from family, friends and associates regarding personal and business affairs, military matters, and Democratic politics; miscellaneous other materials and photographs.
10 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Mrs. Andrew Ness (donor no. 712 ) in 1941; and from the W. K. Foundation (donor no. 1165 ).
The collection is open to research.
Portions of the collection relating to Parkhurst's Civil War services and family history have been microfilmed. The entire collection (unfilmed and filmed is described in this finding aid. A separate finding aid describes the microfilmed material.
John G. Parkhurst was born April 17, 1824 at Oneida Castle, New York. He attended Oneida Academy, then studied law in the office of N. F. Graves. He was admitted to the bar in 1847. He moved to Coldwater, Michigan in 1849 and open up a law practice. With the outbreak of the Civil War, Governor Blair appointed Parkhurst to be lieutenant colonel of the 9th Michigan Infantry. He was taken prisoner at Murfreesboro in July 1862, spent three months in a Southern prison, and was exchanged in December 1862. He served as lieutenant colonel and colonel in the 9th Michigan Infantry, provost marshal of the 14th Army Corps and of the Military District of Tennessee, and was brevet brigadier general of U. S. Volunteers. He served under General George H. Thomas
From 1866 to 1869 he was marshal of the Michigan District. A life-long Democrat ran for various offices, usually without success. President Cleveland rewarded his service to his party and to the nation, naming Parkhurst as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States to Belgium. He served from 1888 to 1889. In 1893, President Cleveland commissioned him postmaster of Coldwater where he served until 1897.
Parkhurst had many other interests. As early as 1849, he was engaged in the insurance business which he continued throughout his life. He also invested in farm lands and participated in veterans organizations. He died May 6, 1906.
The John G. Parkhurst collection consists of correspondence from family, friends and associates regarding personal and business affairs, military matters, and Democratic politics; miscellaneous other materials and photograph. the collections has been divided into the following series: Correspondence; John G. Parkhurst Civil War service; John G. Parkhurst diplomatic and other activities; and Other family materials, business records, and miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Belgium.; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868.; Business records.; Coldwater (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1884.; Elections--Michigan--1886.; Elections--Michigan--1887.; Elections--Michigan--1888.; Elections--Michigan--1892.; Elections--Michigan--1894.; Elections--Michigan--1896.; Elections--Michigan--1897.; Fires--Illinois--Chicago.; Great Fire, Chicago, Ill., 1871.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Homemakers--Michigan--Coldwater.; Journalists--Michigan--Coldwater.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Oneida Castle (N.Y.); Paris (France); Parkhurst, John G. (John Gibson), 1824-1906.; Public utilities--Michigan.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 9th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women--Michigan--Coldwater.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Children.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contributors:
Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Campau, Daniel J., 1852-1927.; Coldwater Electric Street Railway.; Coldwater Gas Light Company.; Coldwater Light and Power Company.; Custer National Monument Association.; Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.; Duffield, Henry Martyn, 1842-1912.; Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943.; Greenback Labor Party (U.S.); Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Parkhurst, Stephen.; Roosevelt, Robert Barnwell, 1829-1906.; Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906.; Society of the Army of the Cumberland.; Stockbridge, Mr. (Francis Brown), 1826-1894.; Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Weston, Isaac M. (Isaac Mellen), 1845-1899.; White, Peter, 1830-1908.; Wilkinson, William Henry, 1819-1890.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  The great bulk of the collection consists of correspondence of Parkhurst and other members of his family. Except for period of time when Parkhurst was away from home, the letters are largely incoming. Copies were not made of responses.
  - Pre-Civil War
    - 1802, 1823, 1831, 1839 (Box 1)
    - 1840-1859, 20 folders (Box 1)
  - Civil War years
    Because his Civil War service was pivotal in his life, letters from this period warranted further description. From 1861 to 1866, Parkhurst wrote one hundred and five letters to his sisters and to his young daughter. In these letters, he describes Fort Wayne and the steamer Mississippi; also the camp at West Point, Ky., with a drawing of the streets of tents and of his tent in particular. He writes of sickness in camp, his duties, marches, guerrillas, Vallandigham's crossing, and skirmishes with Morgan. He tells about the crops, the flies, and spring floods. He describes the beauties of the countryside, the conditions of the roads and the supply lines, and the fighting around Murfreesboro, Chattanooga and at Chickamauga, and the siege of Atlanta, with a special account of the battle of Stones River. He also tells of the forming of the 23rd Brigade, the exchange of prisoners, and mustering out. There are comments on General Thomas and a great many on his own family and personal affairs. Associated with these letters are the several files of other Civil War documents that he preserved, his recollection of the Battle of Stones River, and his involvement with veterans groups. A microfilm copy of this portion of the Parkhurst papers is available for interlibrary loan.
    - 1860-1864, 18 folders (Box 1)
    - 1865, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Post Civil War
    - 1866-1873, 41 folders (Box 2)
    - 1874-1884, 37 folders (Box 3)
    - 1885-1890, 45 folders (Box 4)
    - 1891-June 1896, 38 folders (Box 5)
    - July 1896-June 1901, 48 folders (Box 6)
    - July 1901-1906, 46 folders (Box 7)
    - 1907-1914 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Undated, 45 folders (Box 8)
    - Undated, 28 folders (Box 9)
- John G. Parkhurst Civil War service
  - War-time documents and remembrances
    (microfilm copy of this portion of the Parkhurst papers is available)
    - List of prisoners of war captured by troops under command of General George H. Thomas 1864 (Box 9)
    - List of persons indicted for treason in Tennessee during the Civil War (Box 9)
    - Recollections of the Battle of Stones River, account dated February 6, 1890 (Box 9)
    - Claim made by General Parkhurst for the loss of two horses in the Civil War (Box 9)
    - Civil War map of middle Tennessee
      (now located in library's map collection; not microfilmed)
  - Post-war veterans affairs
    - Letters from General George H. Thomas and wife 1867-1885 (Box 9)
    - Pension claim of General John G. Parkhurst 1899-1900 (Box 9)
    - Veterans organizations and reunion miscellanea (Box 9)
      (microfilm copy available)
    - Jonathan D. Hale file (claims against the government and land speculation in the Tennessee-Kentucky border area) 1865-1883 (Box 9)
- John G. Parkhurst diplomatic and other activities
  - Letters of recommendations of appointment of John G. Parkhurst as Mail Agent 1857 (Box 9)
  - Regarding his appointment as minister to Belgium 1888-1889 (Box 9)
  - Testimonial to John G. Parkhurst from people of Oneida County, New York (Box 9)
  - Garfield National Monument Fund 1882-1883, 3 folders (Box 9)
- Other family materials, business records, and miscellaneous
  - Parkhurst family correspondence, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Stephen Parkhurst papers 1792, 1823, 1844, 1848 (Box 10)
  - Letters to Maggie Parkhurst from Henry written from Brussels, Belgium 1889-1896, 14 folders (Box 10)
    (in French)
  - Legal papers 1850-1892 (Box 10)
  - Family legal papers (Box 10)
  - Family history notes (Box 10)
  - Manuscripts of compositions and poetry by members of the Parkhurst and Starr families, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Lists of names for election notices 1827 (Box 10)
  - Constitution of the Oneida Castle Literary Society 1847 (Box 10)
  - Oneida Castle Senate record book 1844-1850 (Box 10)
    (volume also includes Justice of the Peace judgment book)
  - Diary of Mrs. Helen Parkhurst Starr (Parkhurst's sister), January-July 1868 (Box 10)
    (the volume also includes miscellaneous jottings and some clippings)
  - Receipts [sample], 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Insurance Company statements (Box 10)
  - Printed miscellanea, 8 folders (Box 10)
    (include programs, announcements, etc)
  - Invitations (sample) (Box 10)
  - Personal calling cards (Box 10)
  - Book publishing announcements (Box 10)
  - Political circulars, etc. (Box 10)
  - Miscellanea (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Box 10)
    Portraits, most unidentified, including two Civil War portraits.
    (see also Uax tintypes)
  - Land patents, certificates of appointments, legal miscellaneous (Folder Ac)
  - Hanover Fire Insurance Co. (monthly accounts current) (Folder Ac)
  - Germania Fire Insurance Co. (monthly accounts) (Folder Ac)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Alger, R.A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.
June 21, 1886, Feb. 2, 1897, Apr. 12, 1897
Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.
Sept. 1, 1861, Feb. 17, 1863
Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.
May 2, 1901
Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.
Mar. 12, 1894, Apr. 16, 1894, Feb. 6, 1895
Campau, Daniel J., 1852-1927.
Sept. 23, 1890, Apr. 2, 1891, Sept. 18, 1891, Oct. 1892, Oct. 9, 1896
Custer National Monument Association.
Oct. 3, 1876
Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.
1879-1897
Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.
July 14, 1880, Oct. 17, 1884, 1885, Jan. 4, 1886, May 31, 1886, Oct. 20, 1886
1887, 1888, Nov. 6, 1890, Nov. 11, 1890, 1892, 1894, May 16, 1895, Sept. 11, 1895, 1896, Dec. 8, 1897, May 27 and 31, 1898, Nov. 10, 1899
Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.
1863, 1865, Apr. 10, 1870, 1878, 1879, Oct. 14, 1881, 1882, 1883, Feb. 21, 1884, Mar. 21, 1885, Apr. 22, 1886
Duffield, Henry Martyn, 1842-1912.
Dec. 1, 1862, Oct. 27, 1864, 1865, 1866, Aug. 1, 1869, 1879
Apr. 19, 1881, 1883, 1884, 1886, 1887, May 24, 1888, Nov. 2, 1888
1890, 1897, May 31, 1898, Sept. 19, 1898, 1899, 1900, 1904, May 7, 1906
Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943.
June 27, 1890
Greenback Labor Party (U.S.)
Sept. 12, 1888, Oct. 2, 1888
Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875.
May 15, 1862
McMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Jan. 30, 1895
Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.
Apr. 15, 1889, May 7, 1895, Apr. 9, 1897
Roosevelt, Robert Barnwell, 1829-1906.
1888-1889
Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906.
Nov. 15, 1893
Stockbridge, Mr. (Francis Browne), 1826-1894.
Apr. 2, 1890
Society of the Army of the Cumberland.
[correspondence throughout]
Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.
Letters, 1867-1885 [Folder 374]
Weston, Isaac M. (Isaac Mellen), 1845-1899.
1885-1888, 1890-1891, 1893-1894, 1896
White, Peter Quintard, 1830-1908.
Jan. 25, 1893, Mar. 7, 1893, Mar. 7, 1897
Related Material
Michigan State University Archives and Historical Collection has a separate John G. Parkhurst collection.